This is the Mandalay Bay South
Convention Center, and for 3 days in
April, it turns into an unintentional
display of everything that's wrong with
American youth sports.
The transformation begins on Good Friday
of Easter weekend, when crews turn the
massive Bayside exhibit halls into
uniform row after uniform row of
volleyball courts, 123 to be exact. The
next 2 days will be absurdly busy. Every
individual court will be played on
non-stop by a rotating set of eight
teams from 7:30 a.m. to 9:30 p.m.,
making for just under 1,000 teams in
total passing through the event. Each
team, composed of on average 10 players,
two coaches, and at least an equal
number of parents and family members,
means conservatively about 24 people per
team, so about 24,000 people at the
event. With all the whistles, squeaking
shoes, and screaming U11 to U15 girls,
it'll be [music] uncomfortably loud.
Without a single window, with absurdly
long concession lines, and absurdly
priced concessions, to the uninvested
onlooker, it would all seem an
impressive, but rather unappealing event
to spend much time at. But, to the
players, coaches, and parents duking it
out on the court,
>> [music]
>> this weekend means everything.
This youth tournament, the Red Rock
Rave, is sanctioned by USA Volleyball,
which, as the sport's governing body,
grants the tournament [music] status as
a national qualifier. And to everyone in
the club volleyball ecosystem, national
qualifiers are a big deal. Depending on
which division a team is in, if they
win, or place second or third in some,
they'll get a bid to go to USAV
Nationals in either Indianapolis or
Minneapolis. Getting to play at
Nationals represents a massive
achievement for clubs, coaches, and
players. So, right now, for every one of
the 950 teams in Las Vegas, a bid is the
dream, even if there are only 31 up for
grabs in total. And they're all paying a
pretty penny for the privilege of
chasing the dream.
For the clubs, the regional host, the
hotels, the sanctioning body, this
tournament means big business. To play
in this tournament, each of these teams
paid $950,
and that is just the tip of the iceberg.
Plastered on the court map distributed
around the event is the logo of the
company facilitating lodging for this
event, Casey Sports Housing, reminding
each parent at the tournament that this
is what's called a stay-to-play
>> [music]
>> event. This term is just what it sounds
like, a quid pro quo. Book hotel
reservations through a handful of
options that the tournament has
partnered [music] with, and your team
will be allowed to play. In this
situation, it limits options to the
Mandalay, Bay, Luxor, and a host of
other gaming and non-gaming hotels,
while still offering pretty competitive
rates. It's a pain, but it's hard to get
around when organizing massive events
like this. In other markets with more
alternatives like Airbnb, Vrbo, or an
extra room in a family or friend's
house, stay-to-play can feel
restricting, and the rates can also feel
artificially high. Whether fair
criticisms or not, stay-to-play brings
into focus the travel cost.
There are only a few teams here locally.
The rest are from everywhere: Colorado,
California, Idaho, Texas, Missouri, even
Hawaii. Three nights at a hotel then,
along with airfare or gas, and a mom and
a daughter are looking at a bare minimum
of $1,000, making their $95 share of the
tournament fee, if split between 10
girls, easy to overlook. Throw in a
sibling or a spouse coming along, and
the number goes up to ballpark $1,500
[music]
for the weekend in travel. The costs
continue to accumulate. Outside food and
drink are prohibited, so if you don't
smuggle it in, you're resigned to $12
chicken sandwiches, $10 slices of pizza,
or, especially popular with the kids,
$16 acai bowls throughout the three
days. Tournament merch is critical for
the kids to proudly show off they've
been to a big tournament, so another $50
on a hoodie. Should the parent actually
want to watch their kid play, there's an
entry fee of $27.50
plus processing, or a $65.40
three-day [music] pass. For the rest of
the family back home, these games are
streamed, but the entry-level
subscription for that [music] service is
$44.85.
Then there are the coaches. While the
kids' coaches are hardly compensated,
they're at least put up in a hotel and
given a travel stipend, which parents
are also on the hook for. They pay for
this, as well as the tournament fee,
through what are called club dues. Way
back in July, when teams were selected
after the tryout window opened, parents
agreed that on top of paying for their
kid to get four to six of these
tournaments, they'd also pay their share
to rent gym space, compensate a coach,
cover the club's insurance, and
generally keep the lights on. These run
about $2,500 to $7,000, depending on the
club, age group, and travel. While the
total may differ widely, what's common
in the space is for these club dues to
be pretty opaque. You're told the total,
but you're not exactly sure where that
money is going.
Put all of this together, for your kid
to play club volleyball with the travel,
food, entrance fee, and every other
nickel and diming that comes with each
tournament, and you're looking at a
$2,000 weekend, at the very least. Now
multiply that by four tournaments, then
add, say, $3,500 in dues, and a pretty
typical competitive club experience is
now nearing $11,500
for just the season. And if a kid starts
as a 12-year-old and ends up pursuing it
all the way through their 18s year, the
last as a junior, there are six more
years of these $11,500 seasons coming.
It's an extremely expensive investment
for a budding hobby or passion. But club
parents aren't treating this like any
old hobby.
Just like the kid that's pursuing the
ever-meaningful bid, the parent is
pursuing a dream, too. The dream of a
college scholarship. Of course, the odds
here are similarly small to the chances
of getting a bid. At just this one
tournament, there are nearly the same
amount of players as there are in all
Division I volleyball, without even
considering how many are on scholarship.
But anything that could potentially help
cover costs of an education that's
anywhere from $25,000 to $65,000 a year
or beyond feels worth pursuing. There
are lower levels of college play, too,
Division II, Division III, NAIA, but
none offer full scholarships that pay
all college dues and room and board. Not
all even provide partial scholarships to
cover the ballooning costs of college.
But the dream is too deeply ingrained to
look too closely at the numbers. The
people set to turn a profit off these
youth endeavors won't allow it. Drowning
out the less than stellar statistics
that fewer than 6% of youth volleyball
players will play in college and that
only 1.2% will play Division 1 are the
posts from tournament organizers on how
many college coaches will be in
attendance at this tournament. And it's
more than unlikely you'll run into any
reference to those slim odds when the
local club only brings up the college
players they have produced when trying
to secure kids' commitment and their
parents' club dues. The dream is even
culturally perpetuated, too, as it's a
massive honor within a parent's social
circle to send a kid into college
athletics. Something they can boast
about, something they believe serves as
a badge of good parenting. This dream,
shared by the kid, their coach, and the
parent, is so pervasive, so strongly
held, and such a money generator that
private equity has now gotten involved.
Across Red Rock Rave's 123 courts,
there's an increasingly common, albeit
pretty minimalist and easy to miss logo
adorning jerseys. It reads LOVB, but is
pronounced [music] love, and it
represents the most dramatic private
equity invasion into the sport. League
One Volleyball is technically a
professional league with a highly unique
business model. Only 2 years old, the
league has six teams with a few more on
the way. What makes it novel is that
this league also owns 90 youth
volleyball clubs around the US. This at
the youth level is presented as a real
plus. It means that the league supports
the grassroots of American volleyball.
It means there's a direct pipeline to
the pros. Furthering the excited buy-in
from players and parents alike, LOVB is
equal parts aspirational and empowering.
The company is proudly women-led and, in
their words, committed to empowering
women both on and off the court.
>> [music]
>> And seemingly each team in the league is
at least in part owned by professional
or former professional athletes, also
often female. For those playing at, say
Club V in Salt Lake City, well the
club's name hasn't changed, [music] well
the coaches and leadership has remained
the same, there's now the common
occurrence of one of the Love Salt Lake
City players walking into their gym.
It's all very exciting because it just
makes the big [music] leagues feel more
possible. But for Love, the grassroots
involvement isn't just something they're
doing out of the goodness of their
hearts, and it's certainly not why
they've received private equity buy-in.
To run this upstart professional league,
Love needs those club dues. And to
maximize the return, private equity
needs to see those club dues go up.
The money that's propped Love up has
come through a few different channels.
It has brand deals with Adidas and
Skims, it has broadcast deals with USA
and ESPN, and it's been backed by some
major investments by private equity
firms. The league has garnered somewhere
near $200 million in total funding led
by the Atwater Group and supplemented by
Ares Management Fund and Left Lane
Capital, while some individual teams are
now owned by groups like Synergy Sports
Capital. To make the private equity ties
even deeper, Love CEO Caitlin Gao came
from Bain Capital. And what's brought
all this private equity interest into
the space is not the upside of the
professional league, but the confidence
in a robust outlook for the youth
[music] side going forward. In Atwater's
words, it's not just about generating
returns, but also leveraging their
experience in media and entertainment to
engage fans in exciting ways and inspire
the next generation of exceptional
athletes. Effectively, they believe in
Love as a way to further perpetuate the
dreams that have parents spending more
and more money on youth sports. This is
private equity strategy beyond
volleyball, too. Because not only is the
space a $40 billion a year sector, it's
growing at 8 to 10% a year, and most
importantly, the system is
self-perpetuating. Parents are
increasingly finding themselves in a
spending war for more specialization and
more training time, so more money goes
into the machine.
It all creates a flow that looks like
this. The most money and the most
players at the grassroots level with a
disproportionate amount of money in in
to the players rising up the triangle.
And because of this structure, the
incentives, from the perspective of the
development of the game, are skewed.
There's the most pressure on youth
sports not to teach the game first and
foremost, but to sell dreams of bids and
college scholarships so that the gym
stays full and the club dues keep
flowing in. Then, of course, there's the
issue of access [music] in the first
place. As a player ages out of
introductory public programs and into
middle school and high school sports
that are publicly funded, these publicly
funded programs are so competitive and
carry so few players that a kid
practically has to play club to make the
team. And if club costs upward of
$10,000 a year, the sport immediately
turns a massive swath of the population
away. Beyond the cost, the travel and
time away from work is extreme. And then
there's the cultural factor that the
game begins to feel like it's only for
the wealthy and upper middle class. All
this has become so ingrained in the
American athletic consciousness that it
all feels second nature. But this
structure isn't the norm elsewhere.
This is called La Masia. Located in the
suburbs of Barcelona, Spain, this is
hallowed ground in the soccer or
football world. This is the historical
youth training site for FC Barcelona's
up-and-comers. Like at a competitive
volleyball club in the US, the kids here
were recruited and vetted and are
continually pushed to grow as players.
Unlike in the US, these kids, some of
which grow up to be Lionel Messi, Andres
Iniesta, Lamine Yamal, a few of the
game's biggest names in the past few
decades, do not pay to be here. Rather,
the opposite. They're being trained in
the club's ways while also getting paid.
In this situation, the financial aspect
of the triangle is effectively flipped.
As FC Barcelona is one of the world's
largest and most important clubs,
there's a lot of money coming in at the
top of the triangle, which it then
reinvests in its youth development to
ensure that the club is able to stay one
of the largest in the world by
developing world-class talent.
Perhaps it's unfair to compare a startup
volleyball league, a country that shown
the appetite at the youth level for the
sport, but has never developed its own
domestic professional league
successfully with one of the largest
clubs in the world's biggest sport. So,
instead take baseball. It's America's
national pastime and it's a profitable
entity at the highest level in the US.
And yet, the extreme financial demands
of youth baseball still exist in a very
similar manner to those in volleyball.
To keep up with your peers, you can't
just play at your high school or middle
school, you need to play travel
baseball. The dream here is alluring,
too, perhaps even more so. A high-level
high school player can get drafted
directly into Major League Baseball and
receive a multi-million dollar signing
bonus at 18 years old. For those that
aren't quite as promising, there's still
the college option and the ever-alluring
scholarship.
This isn't just a baseball issue. In all
American sports that generate revenue at
the professional level, hockey, American
football, basketball, little of the
massive profit brought in from endless
sponsorship and massive broadcast deals
is making it down to the youth level to
fund the development of the next
generation as college athletics sever
the connection of the pipeline. This is
a uniquely American problem as the US's
massive, expensive university system
also happens to be the dream destination
for top athletes. They want to play a
sport in college. Colleges offer
scholarships, stipends, and due to
increasingly relaxed rules over what is
considered an amateur athlete, some ways
to make some money, but they don't
invest in youth programs like FC
Barcelona and they shield the major
revenue professional leagues from the
pressure to invest in youth sports, too.
Rather than going through a development
pipeline where the highest levels water
the grassroots with access to the game,
coaches, and further and further
training for those that show the most
promise, in the US it's increasingly on
the drive of kids and the pocketbooks of
parents to begin opening opportunities
for higher-level play. It's all
hyper-individualist, hyper-competitive,
>> [music]
>> hyper-American.
But it just isn't working.
Across the sports landscape in the US,
there are indicators. At the highest
level of American sports, there's a
notable uptick in second generation
professionals. Ethan Holliday, who
signed the largest baseball signing
bonus out of high school, is the son of
legendary baseball player Matt Holliday.
Ashlyn O'Neal and the sisters Madison
and Avery Skinner are dominant for the
US volleyball team and are daughters of
former NBA players. It's not nepotism.
These young athletes are all extremely
deserving, driven, and capable. Rather,
these second generation stars are
becoming more common because their
athletic advantages are matched by
financial advantages. They've [music]
had the access through their
professional athlete parents to elite
training and high-level coaching their
whole lives. In soccer, no country has
more youth players than the US, but
because of barriers to access, clubs
incentivized to turn a profit and
compete for meaningless tournament
results rather than player development,
the US men's side failed to qualify for
the 2018 World Cup while tiny Iceland
held its own against mighty Argentina.
And in 2022, the men's team was knocked
out comfortably by the Netherlands,
[music]
whose population is slightly smaller
than that of the state of New York.
Then there's Norway. At the last Winter
Olympics, the nation of under 6 million
stacked up 18 gold medals, six more than
the [music] US, and 41 total medals,
eight more than the US. In the US, it's
common for older generations of coaches
and leaders to lament the fact that
everyone now gets a participation
[music] trophy. Not only is this not
true, as youth sports have never been
more competitive here than they are now,
but the nation might benefit from it.
Norway's sporting success is largely
attributed to its youth model that
prioritizes finding joy in the sport and
an internal love for improving at the
practice rather than just focusing on
results and scores and finishing
positions. A naysayer might push back
and say that it is culture and heritage
pushing this tiny nation in front of the
US in the Winter Olympics. That'd be
wrong. Their best triathletes are the
best in the world. Their distance
runners are beating East Africans and
Americans alike. Even their best men's
beach volleyball partnership is better
than any the US can produce. The United
States is unapologetically a
sports-obsessed nation. It's a massive
nation, too. And yet, in sports that the
rest of the world participates in, the
US does just okay. The talent is here,
but it's just not getting the
opportunity.
The problem is bigger than American
national teams in the highest reaches of
athletic achievement. It's a public
health issue. In a 2025 hearing, the
subcommittee on early childhood,
elementary, and secondary education
[music] discussed the negative
ramifications that declining numbers in
youth sports has on kids. With 70% of
all US kids quitting organized sports by
13, there's an ever-increasing number of
kids losing out on the benefits that
sports bring. Without sports, kids are
more likely to think negatively of
themselves, they're more likely to
become obese, they're less likely to
succeed in school, less likely to be an
active parent and raise an active child.
Hyper-specialization is burning kids
out. Hyper-competitive, results-oriented
approaches are leaving too many kids in
the cold. What seems increasingly clear
is that when we push on our youth
programs to produce wins, winners, and
more and more dollars, we're setting
ourselves up to lose in the long run.
Misaligned incentives and subsequent bad
outcomes also happens to be, in the
broadest sense, the story of Mustard's
latest episode of Unsealed called The
Virus That Infected Boeing, which is
available right now on the sponsor of
this video, Nebula. If you're watching
this video, you're likely aware of
Mustard's YouTube channel, and if you're
anything like me, you too are always
excited when their team releases another
spellbinding story with some of the most
amazingly detailed and cinematic 3D
motion graphics about some of the most
interesting aviation and engineering
stories out there. I was genuinely so
excited to find out that accompanying
Mustard's last YouTube release on the
context behind the first Boeing 707
barrel roll was an episode of Unsealed
that tells the larger story about
Boeing's rise and its problems. I really
think it illustrates just how valuable a
product Nebula is. Now, I may be biased
because I have a role in shaping what
Nebula is as a streaming service, but
because it's a platform designed by
creators, we can run the platform in a
way that allows everyone on the platform
to push really good content in that
direction. And Unsealed is a perfect
example. Unsealed is a series that falls
under the Nebula Plus umbrella, meaning
when the Mustard team puts all the work
their videos require to produce an
airtight script and stunning visuals,
they're naturally going to come across
storylines and ideas that don't
perfectly fit the video at hand. But
rather than tossing those out, with
Nebula, they become another standalone
video. The upshot is that everyone wins.
Fans of the creator now have another
20-minute hyper-detailed story to dive
into, Nebula adds another banger to its
catalog, and the Mustard team makes the
most of all the research they put into a
similar story. And Nebula Plus is just
one of the perks of the streaming
platform. There are Nebula first videos
that release early and without ad reads
that allow you to stay a week ahead on
some of your favorite series like Tom
Scott's England, which brings all the
exploratory intrigue and joy of
discovery of the Tom Scott videos of old
to Tom's homeland. Then, if you like our
content, there's just so much more of it
available through Nebula as Nebula
originals. Whether it's our comedy stuff
like Abolish Everything, our travel
competition Jetlag: The Game, or our
documentary projects like Scav, we've
now put a whole lot of content we're
really proud of on Nebula the past few
years. If you'd like to give it a try,
use my link
nebula.tv/wendoverproductions
to get 50% off an annual subscription.
That's just $30 a year or $2.50 per
month. It's not a lot, but it would mean
a lot to us, so thanks.